<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Psychology | CSS-Synosys</title>
    <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/tag/psychology/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://css-synosys.github.io/tag/psychology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Psychology</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://css-synosys.github.io/media/logo_hu_8314fbf1d9759f2e.png</url>
      <title>Psychology</title>
      <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/tag/psychology/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preprint on decision-making and large language models</title>
      <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/post/preprint-25/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://css-synosys.github.io/post/preprint-25/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can large language models help us understand the psychology of risky choice?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Our colleague &lt;strong&gt;Kamil Fulawka&lt;/strong&gt; is the first author of a new preprint that tackles this question. Together with Ralph Hertwig and Dirk Wulff, he introduces a scalable approach to analyze participants’ free-text explanations of their decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study shows that LLMs can accurately identify the reasons people give for their lottery choices in more than 92% of cases. These verbal reports reveal systematic patterns: people’s reasoning depends strongly on the structure of the choice problem rather than being fixed across individuals. Models built on these reason profiles also achieve higher predictive accuracy than prospect theory, one of the most established frameworks in decision science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By demonstrating the scientific value of verbal data, this work opens new avenues for developing context-aware models of human decision-making.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;👉 A more detailed description of the analysis, as well as the code and data, can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/preprints/psyarxiv/yuzmw_v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Psychology of Digital Propaganda</title>
      <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/project/propaganda/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://css-synosys.github.io/project/propaganda/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Across the globe, worries are growing about the unchecked power of social media and manipulative content, further enhanced by generative AI. As viral content is believed to shape public opinions, the question of how exactly these forces influence individual and collective beliefs, attitudes, and behavior has never been more urgent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our research focuses on Digital Propaganda, which we understand as orchestrated efforts by various actors—be they political, corporate, or ideological—to influence the public for their own benefit. Leveraging user data and the attention-maximization of feed algorithms, today’s social media and digital platforms enable these campaigns to operate with greater precision and scale than ever before, far surpassing what was possible with television or radio alone. By personalizing messages, repeating them relentlessly, simplifying complex issues into stark narratives, and amplifying emotionally charged content, this new digital environment intensifies the potential to shock, polarize, and manipulate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although these tactics clearly exploit known cognitive biases and emotional reactivity, we still lack precise causal evidence of how exactly they shape people’s feelings, beliefs, and behaviors. Many assume digital propaganda wields manipulative power, yet a deeper understanding of which elements of human cognition and behavior are truly affected—and in what ways—remains elusive. Through large-scale experimentation, computational modeling, and psychologically driven and AI-supported analysis of social media content, we aim to bring robust empirical evidence to the table to uncover these mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, by bridging these knowledge gaps, we seek to lay the groundwork for evidence-based psychological interventions that empower individuals to recognize and resist manipulative strategies. At the same time, our findings will offer crucial insights for policymakers and platform regulators, helping them craft balanced measures that safeguard users from harmful content while upholding the essential values of open dialogue and informed participation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
