<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Kamil Fuławka | CSS-Synosys</title>
    <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/author/kamil-fu%C5%82awka/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://css-synosys.github.io/author/kamil-fu%C5%82awka/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Kamil Fuławka</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://css-synosys.github.io/author/kamil-fu%C5%82awka/avatar_hu_30334330dd6970db.jpg</url>
      <title>Kamil Fuławka</title>
      <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/author/kamil-fu%C5%82awka/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kamil Fuławka</title>
      <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/author/kamil-fu%C5%82awka/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://css-synosys.github.io/author/kamil-fu%C5%82awka/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Kamil is a postdoc in the junior research group &amp;ldquo;Computational Social Science.&amp;rdquo; Trained as a psychologist, he specializes in understanding how individuals make decisions under risk and uncertainty. His core research interests focus on the (dis)adaptive roles of emotions and heuristics in decision-making and the dynamics of the decision-making process itself. Kamil’s research motivation is fueled by challenges in health-related decisions, such as vaccine hesitancy and food choices, and the impact of contemporary affective (emotional) propaganda on political preferences. His work integrates various methods, including computational modeling, behavioral and process-tracing experiments, and automated analysis of subjective reports with large language models.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preprint on decision-making and large language models</title>
      <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/post/preprint-25/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://css-synosys.github.io/post/preprint-25/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can large language models help us understand the psychology of risky choice?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Our colleague &lt;strong&gt;Kamil Fulawka&lt;/strong&gt; is the first author of a new preprint that tackles this question. Together with Ralph Hertwig and Dirk Wulff, he introduces a scalable approach to analyze participants’ free-text explanations of their decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study shows that LLMs can accurately identify the reasons people give for their lottery choices in more than 92% of cases. These verbal reports reveal systematic patterns: people’s reasoning depends strongly on the structure of the choice problem rather than being fixed across individuals. Models built on these reason profiles also achieve higher predictive accuracy than prospect theory, one of the most established frameworks in decision science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By demonstrating the scientific value of verbal data, this work opens new avenues for developing context-aware models of human decision-making.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;👉 A more detailed description of the analysis, as well as the code and data, can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/preprints/psyarxiv/yuzmw_v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Complex Systems in Biology (and Beyond)</title>
      <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/teaching/complex_system_biology/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://css-synosys.github.io/teaching/complex_system_biology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Opal: &lt;a href=&#34;https://bildungsportal.sachsen.de/opal/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Link here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;description&#34;&gt;Description:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This course offers an overview and basic understanding of complex dynamic phenomena in biological, physical and social systems. The focus is on biological systems but with a comparative perspective that reveals the universal principles underlying complex behavior across different domains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Students will learn to think about biological systems as complex adaptive systems, where interactions between molecules, cells, or organisms give rise to emergent properties that cannot be understood from studying individual components in isolation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;course-structure&#34;&gt;Course Structure:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part I: Foundations of Complexity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What makes a system complex?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Networks and connectivity patterns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dynamical systems in biology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emergence and self-organization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part II: Biological Applications&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gene regulatory networks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Metabolic networks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Neural networks and brain dynamics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ecological networks and food webs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evolution as a complex process&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part III: Comparative Perspectives&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Social systems as complex adaptive systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Physical systems and universality&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Common patterns across domains&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Modeling approaches and tools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;practical-components&#34;&gt;Practical Components:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course includes hands-on exercises using:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Network analysis tools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Computational modeling (agent-based models, differential equations)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data analysis of real biological datasets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Case studies from current research&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;assessment-components&#34;&gt;Assessment Components:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presentation (40%)&lt;/strong&gt;: Research presentation on a selected complex biological system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Written Exam (60%)&lt;/strong&gt;: Theoretical knowledge and problem-solving&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;prerequisites&#34;&gt;Prerequisites:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basic biology background (cell biology, genetics, ecology)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mathematical foundations (calculus, basic statistics)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some programming experience helpful but not required&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;target-audience&#34;&gt;Target Audience:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This course is designed for students in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Biology and life sciences&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bioinformatics and computational biology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Physics with biological interests&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Systems science and related fields&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Statistical Modeling for Online Behavior Data</title>
      <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/teaching/stats_model/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://css-synosys.github.io/teaching/stats_model/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Opal: &lt;a href=&#34;https://bildungsportal.sachsen.de/opal/auth/RepositoryEntry/48880648204/CourseNode/1743474776839555003&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Link here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time Thursdays, 5. DS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Location BAR/0I89&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Department Computer Science&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modules INF-BAS3 (Software- und Web-Engineering)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Language English&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assessment oral exam&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;description&#34;&gt;Description:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Online platforms generate vast amounts of behavioral data, including subjective ratings (e.g., likes, stars, reactions) and objective engagement metrics (e.g., views, clicks, watch time). While machine learning excels at predicting user behavior, statistical modeling—a cornerstone of empirical research—is critical for interpretable analysis. It helps uncover relationships between user behavior and various factors (e.g., how demographics influence engagement patterns) and enables causal inference in experiments (e.g., measuring the impact of different feed-ranking algorithms on user experience). These methods are widely used in UX research, product analytics, and A/B testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This course provides a hands-on introduction to statistical modeling in R, focusing on methods most useful for analyzing behavioral data. We&amp;rsquo;ll cover key concepts and progress to model selection based on outcome type. Topics include logistic regression for binary outcomes (e.g., like/dislike reactions), ordinal regression for rating scales, beta regression for continuous feedback (e.g., sliders), and hierarchical models for nested data (e.g., multiple ratings from the same users). In the end, you&amp;rsquo;ll not only know which model to use but also how to effectively visualize and communicate your findings through clear, interpretable result presentations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No prior statistical modeling experience is required. If you&amp;rsquo;re familiar with Python or similar languages, the transition to R should be easy. All scripts and exercises are provided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;schedule&#34;&gt;Schedule:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part 1: General Introduction&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 1 Introduction to statistical modeling: goals and principles&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 2 Linear regression: the foundational model, applications and limitations&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part 2: Selected Generalized Linear Models&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 1 Logistic regression 1: analysis of likes and dislikes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 2 Logistic regression 2: multivariate analysis&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 3 Ordinal regression 1: stars and other likert-type ratings&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 4 Ordinal regression 2: modeling distributional parameters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 5 Beta regression 1: slider-type ratings&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 6 Beta regression 2: modeling distributional parameters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 7 Interim summary, additional exercises, and other GLMs&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part 3: Experimental design &amp;amp; hierarchical models&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 1 Modeling between- and within-individual experimental designs&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 2 Hierarchical models 1: introduction&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 3 Hierarchical models 2: logistic and ordinal regression&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 4 Hierarchical models 3: Beta regression&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 5 Final session, Q&amp;amp;A, discussion and feedback&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Psychology of Digital Propaganda</title>
      <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/project/propaganda/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://css-synosys.github.io/project/propaganda/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Across the globe, worries are growing about the unchecked power of social media and manipulative content, further enhanced by generative AI. As viral content is believed to shape public opinions, the question of how exactly these forces influence individual and collective beliefs, attitudes, and behavior has never been more urgent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our research focuses on Digital Propaganda, which we understand as orchestrated efforts by various actors—be they political, corporate, or ideological—to influence the public for their own benefit. Leveraging user data and the attention-maximization of feed algorithms, today’s social media and digital platforms enable these campaigns to operate with greater precision and scale than ever before, far surpassing what was possible with television or radio alone. By personalizing messages, repeating them relentlessly, simplifying complex issues into stark narratives, and amplifying emotionally charged content, this new digital environment intensifies the potential to shock, polarize, and manipulate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although these tactics clearly exploit known cognitive biases and emotional reactivity, we still lack precise causal evidence of how exactly they shape people’s feelings, beliefs, and behaviors. Many assume digital propaganda wields manipulative power, yet a deeper understanding of which elements of human cognition and behavior are truly affected—and in what ways—remains elusive. Through large-scale experimentation, computational modeling, and psychologically driven and AI-supported analysis of social media content, we aim to bring robust empirical evidence to the table to uncover these mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, by bridging these knowledge gaps, we seek to lay the groundwork for evidence-based psychological interventions that empower individuals to recognize and resist manipulative strategies. At the same time, our findings will offer crucial insights for policymakers and platform regulators, helping them craft balanced measures that safeguard users from harmful content while upholding the essential values of open dialogue and informed participation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
