<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Latest News | CSS-Synosys</title>
    <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://css-synosys.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Latest News</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://css-synosys.github.io/media/logo_hu_8314fbf1d9759f2e.png</url>
      <title>Latest News</title>
      <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Paper: Understanding Participation Inequality in Online Political Discussions</title>
      <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/post/inequality_online_political_discussions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://css-synosys.github.io/post/inequality_online_political_discussions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A new paper supervised by Philipp Lorenz-Spreen was published yesterday. It addresses a well known problem in digital public spaces. Online debates are often distorted because a loud and sometimes politically extreme minority dominates the conversation while most users remain silent. The study asks how this pattern can change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The team ran a collective field experiment on Reddit. Over four weeks, 520 participants discussed 20 political issues in six private communities. The study tested how monetary incentives and moderation prompts shape participation and discourse quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The findings are clear: Incentives reduced participation inequality, while reminders to “stay civil” unexpectedly increased toxicity. Highly active users posted more when they perceived the environment as polarized. Silent users, in contrast, joined the conversation when discussions felt respectful and constructive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper shows how platform design and perceived discussion climate influence who speaks up and how positive incentives can help make online discourse more inclusive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;👉 &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/sciadv.ady8022&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Read the full article here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How German Members Of Parliament Debate Wealth Taxation On Social Media</title>
      <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/post/20251117_german_taxation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://css-synosys.github.io/post/20251117_german_taxation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a new preprint, Sami Nenno together with Philipp Lorenz-Spreen use LLMs to detect arguments for or against wealth taxation by German members of parliament (MPs) and the business lobby. They analyze their social media communication from 2017 to 2025 on Facebook, Instagram, and X.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study finds that wealth taxation is not among the policy issues most emphasized by MPs on social media. Although attention to the topic occasionally spikes, it never approaches the frequency of other reference issues like unemployment benefits or the nuclear phase-out. Left-wing parties rarely counter opposing arguments, present relatively uniform positions, and primarily justify stricter taxation by invoking rising inequality, injustice, and the responsibility of the wealthy. Conservatives emphasize the supposed threat of losing inherited homes due to higher taxes, while liberals and the far right focus more on economic arguments and often criticize state intervention. On the audience&amp;rsquo;s side, wealth taxation, though infrequently discussed, generates high engagement compared to other issues – especially when stricter taxation is the central message rather than a passing mention. Finally, left-wing parties seldom provide concrete data on inequality or tax exemptions, even though such evidence could strengthen persuasion. The authors conclude that in advocating stricter wealth taxation, left-wing parties likely fail to reach beyond their core electorate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find the full preprint here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/preprints/socarxiv/xn2bu_v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://osf.io/preprints/socarxiv/xn2bu_v1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preprint on text-level Misinformation on Social Media</title>
      <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/post/rac_misinfo_detection/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://css-synosys.github.io/post/rac_misinfo_detection/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a new preprint, Sami Nenno together with Kamil Fuławka and Philipp Lorenz-Spreen from our team and Cornelius Puschmann from the University of Bremen use a new text-based method to detect misinformation on social media. The study analyzes more than half a million posts from all German members of parliament and their official party accounts across Facebook, X, Instagram, and TikTok. Using a novel text-matching approach, the researchers link posts to over 5,000 fact-checking articles and 1,500 community notes. Compared to other methods, they identify ten times as many posts that contain misinformation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their findings show that misinformation remains relatively rare overall but is not evenly distributed. Instead, it clusters around certain parties and topics — in some contexts reaching misinformation rates of about ten percent. By going beyond link-based detection, this approach broadens the scope of misinformation research, providing a more detailed view of where and by whom misinformation is spread, and highlighting the central role of certain parties in its circulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find the full preprint here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/preprints/socarxiv/p6yh9_v1/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://osf.io/preprints/socarxiv/p6yh9_v1/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How people say they feel about uncertainty does not match how they decide</title>
      <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/post/computational_psychiatry/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://css-synosys.github.io/post/computational_psychiatry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How people say they feel about uncertainty does not match how they decide&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Kamil Fuławka from our Computational Social Science group, together with colleagues Yannik Paul and Anya Pedersen from Kiel University, has published a new article in &lt;em&gt;Computational Psychiatry&lt;/em&gt;. The study &lt;em&gt;“Decomposing Intolerance of Uncertainty: No Association With Affective Decision Making in a Community Sample”&lt;/em&gt; addresses a central question in psychology: &lt;strong&gt;How do people respond to uncertainty, and what drives these responses?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intolerance of uncertainty (IU) is considered a key factor across many psychological disorders, from anxiety to obsessive-compulsive symptoms. Yet the mechanisms behind it remain unclear. To explore this, the authors identified three possible pathways: overweighting negative outcomes, distorting probabilities of rare events, and discomfort with missing information. They then mapped these mechanisms onto well-known patterns of human decision-making described by Cumulative Prospect Theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To test this link, the team designed an experiment with 100 participants. Instead of abstract lotteries with money, they used medical scenarios in which people had to choose between two hypothetical painkillers, each with possible side effects and varying chances of success. In one condition, all information was provided upfront. In the other, participants had to discover probabilities by sampling outcomes themselves. This allowed the researchers to compare decision-making under risk with decision-making under uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results confirmed that participants displayed common biases: they overweighed side effects compared to benefits (loss aversion), and they distorted small probabilities. Choices also differed depending on whether information was described or experienced, echoing the well-known description–experience gap. However, none of these behavioral patterns correlated with how strongly individuals reported disliking uncertainty on questionnaires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This finding is important because it suggests that self-reported intolerance of uncertainty and observable decision-making behavior may capture different aspects of the phenomenon. The study points to the need for more precise definitions of IU and for experimental designs that can create stronger affective contexts, possibly with real consequences for behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;👉 &lt;a href=&#34;https://cpsyjournal.org/articles/10.5334/cpsy.140&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Read the full article here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper: Is public broadcasting an amplifier or a gatekeeper of misinformation?</title>
      <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/post/public_broadcasting_misinformation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://css-synosys.github.io/post/public_broadcasting_misinformation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is public broadcasting an amplifier or a gatekeeper of misinformation?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Sami Nenno’s article addressing this question was published in &lt;em&gt;Information, Communication &amp;amp; Society&lt;/em&gt;. He collected fact-checking articles and matched them with subtitles from more than 1,000 news and talk show episodes on German public broadcasting television. The findings show that at least one claim qualifying as misinformation appears in over 12% of talk show episodes and about 2% of news programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such claims are most often made by politicians. While they are sometimes challenged by moderators or other guests, in many cases they remain unaddressed. The misinformation ranges from narratives about migration “pull factors” to climate policy. However, the study finds no evidence that viral online misinformation is being transmitted on television. This suggests that although gatekeeping frequently fails, public broadcasting does not serve as an amplifier either. Instead, two distinct forms emerge: online misinformation, which is often outlandish and unrelated to current public discourse, and misinformation tied to high-profile political events that circulates both online and in traditional media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study underscores the need to broaden the scope of misinformation research and highlights the difficulty journalists face in countering false claims, particularly in live, contentious debates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;👉 &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/1369118X.2025.2561030&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Read the full article here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preprint on decision-making and large language models</title>
      <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/post/preprint-25/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://css-synosys.github.io/post/preprint-25/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can large language models help us understand the psychology of risky choice?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Our colleague &lt;strong&gt;Kamil Fulawka&lt;/strong&gt; is the first author of a new preprint that tackles this question. Together with Ralph Hertwig and Dirk Wulff, he introduces a scalable approach to analyze participants’ free-text explanations of their decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study shows that LLMs can accurately identify the reasons people give for their lottery choices in more than 92% of cases. These verbal reports reveal systematic patterns: people’s reasoning depends strongly on the structure of the choice problem rather than being fixed across individuals. Models built on these reason profiles also achieve higher predictive accuracy than prospect theory, one of the most established frameworks in decision science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By demonstrating the scientific value of verbal data, this work opens new avenues for developing context-aware models of human decision-making.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;👉 A more detailed description of the analysis, as well as the code and data, can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/preprints/psyarxiv/yuzmw_v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What a blast! Philipp Lorenz-Spreen at re:publica 2025</title>
      <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/post/republica/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://css-synosys.github.io/post/republica/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday, our colleague Philipp Lorenz-Spreen took the stage at re:publica 2025 to address one of the most pressing questions of our digital era:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Gesellschaftliche Kipppunkte: Die Spirale aus Aufmerksamkeit und Plattformmacht und wie wir da noch rauskommen”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
(&lt;em&gt;“Societal Tipping Points: The Spiral of Attention and Platform Power – and How We Might Escape It”&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his talk, he explored how notifications, newsfeeds, and social platforms constantly demand our attention – and how this attention has become a source of power with far-reaching political consequences. Moving from everyday habits to systemic impacts, he examined how platform dynamics influence democratic discourse and what needs to change for us to regain agency and foster a healthier public debate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🎥 &lt;strong&gt;Watch the full talk here&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
      &lt;iframe allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share; fullscreen&#34; loading=&#34;eager&#34; referrerpolicy=&#34;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/7j4QIayjAaY?autoplay=0&amp;amp;controls=1&amp;amp;end=0&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;mute=0&amp;amp;start=0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New replication study examines the influence of digital media on democracy</title>
      <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/post/replication/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://css-synosys.github.io/post/replication/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;© [AI] ChatGPT / MPG adapted from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mpg.de/24519906/digital-media-a-threat-to-democracy&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;press release&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The research team systematically replicated the methodology of the original study and used an updated dataset with studies up to March 2024. The results confirm the findings of the original study: Digital media have many problematic effects on democratic processes, in addition to positive ones. On the one hand, they promote political participation and facilitate access to information. On the other hand, they increase polarization, mistrust in institutions, and populist movements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A recent research paper by the Institute for Replication (I4R) analyzes and reviews the results of the 2023 study, ‘A Systematic Review of Worldwide Causal and Correlational Evidence on Digital Media and Democracy,’ by Lorenz-Spreen et al. The replication study, conducted by researchers from Tongji University, the University of Cambridge, and Duke University, confirms the original findings on the relationships between digital media and democracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The replication study supports our findings, and the worrying trends continue,” explains Philipp Lorenz-Spreen, research group leader for Computational Social Science at TU Dresden and research scientist at the Max Planck Institute for Human Development (MPIB) in Berlin. He and Lisa Oswald – both working at the Center for Adaptive Rationality – led the 2023 study. Postdoctoral researcher Lisa Oswald underscores the significance of these findings. “The correlative evidence is mounting that digital media can negatively influence political processes – we see increased polarization, rising mistrust in democratic institutions and media, and a proliferation of misinformation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Replication study: &lt;a href=&#34;https://ideas.repec.org/p/zbw/i4rdps/206.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://ideas.repec.org/p/zbw/i4rdps/206.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Original study: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41562-022-01460-1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41562-022-01460-1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Do Community Notes have a party preference?</title>
      <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/post/community_notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://css-synosys.github.io/post/community_notes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Community notes are supposed to curb disinformation on X - but they themselves follow political patterns. A new data analysis shows that Green Party posts are particularly criticised, but their notes are hardly considered helpful. At the same time, there is no clear political trend in the notes that are actually published. Why is this the case? The article analyses patterns in the distribution and rating of the notes and sheds light on the dynamics that can be derived from the data.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note: This work has not yet been peer reviewed.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;community-notes-instead-of-fact-checks&#34;&gt;Community Notes instead of Fact-checks?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of the year, &lt;a href=&#34;https://about.fb.com/news/2025/01/meta-more-speech-fewer-mistakes/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt; Meta&amp;rsquo;s CEO Mark Zuckerberg announced &lt;/a&gt; that the company was ending its collaboration with independent fact-checkers replacing them with X-style Community Notes (Notes for short). Zuckerberg claimed that fact-checking limited free speech. However, &lt;a href=&#34;https://netzpolitik.org/2025/zuckerbergs-kehrtwende-meta-goes-maga/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;it seems more likely&lt;/a&gt; that this is a concession to Trump and the Republican Party, who accuse fact-checkers of being politically motivated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The accusation that fact-checking is biased in favour of the left or liberal camp is not new and is also made in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nzz.ch/meinung/faktenchecks-zuckerberg-musk-trump-medien-aktivismus-ard-faktenfinder-russland-nordstream-propaganda-fake-news-ld.1867044&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;German-speaking countries&lt;/a&gt;. Of course, fact-checking, like any other journalistic genre, is not free of errors and distortions. However, it is often overlooked that disinformation is frequently associated with right-wing and populist attitudes (Lasser et al. 2022, Törnberg and Chueri 2025). If fact-checks tend to scrutinise right-wing actors, this does not necessarily reveal a bias, but could also reflect an actual asymmetry (Mosleh et al. 2024). For example, a recent study shows that helpful Notes are also more likely to be found in posts from the Republicans (Renault et al. 2025).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog post presents the results of a data analysis of German-language Notes that were rated as helpful or unhelpful at least 20 times and published between January 2024 and January 2025 inclusive. As Notes will also be launched on Facebook and Instagram in the future (initially only in the US), it is worth asking whether there is a focus on parties from a particular ideological spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-do-community-notes-work-on-x&#34;&gt;How do Community Notes work on X?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notes are found as comments on posts and are intended to point out their shortcomings. The Notes for this data analysis show posts as incorrect or unverified (Fig. 1). Notes are written by previously registered users. To register, the account must be older than six months and a verified phone number is required. Because anyone can participate, Notes are often described as the wisdom of the crowd and contrasted with fact-checks as an unbiased alternative. However, this interpretation overlooks the fact that the users who write Notes are not free of political views. Their assessments and comments may therefore be influenced by their own interests or ideological biases (Allen et al. 2022).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://css-synosys.github.io/Söder_Community_Note.png&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; height=&#34;700px&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/Markus_Soeder/status/1879106313956765889&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt; with a community note that was rated as helpful and therefore published.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Precisely because a single registration is enough to write Notes for all posts on X, this is not yet a sign of quality for their correctness. For this reason, registered users can not only write their own Notes, but also rate the Notes of others as helpful or not. To arrive at a final rating, X uses a so-called bridging algorithm. This algorithm takes into account the position of registered users on the political spectrum and requires contributors with different viewpoints to rate the note as helpful (Wojcik et al. 2022). This process is often successful in reflecting the political spectrum, but it also ensures that significantly fewer Notes are published than are actually written.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;which-accounts-of-german-parties-and-politicians-receive-community-notes&#34;&gt;Which accounts of German parties and politicians receive Community Notes?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://css-synosys.github.io/Barplots.html&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;600px&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 2&lt;/strong&gt; Number of posts with Community Notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the following, I present the results of the data analysis. In total, I analysed almost 9000 Notes, of which almost 1700 were considered helpful and therefore published. Figure 2a shows the accounts with the most Notes. Of all accounts on X, Markus Söder, the leader of the CSU and Chief Minister of Bavaria, received the most Notes. However, this changes when it comes to helpful Notes (Fig. 2b). Here, with the exception of Julian Reichelt, former editor-in-chief of Bild and founder of Nius, rather unknown accounts are among the top-ranked accounts. Political accounts, namely those of the CSU and Markus Söder, are only found from 8th place onwards. With this in mind, and also looking at Fig. 2c and Fig. 2d, we can see that the accounts with the most Notes and those with the most helpful Notes are in some cases very different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;which-parties-receive-the-most-community-notes&#34;&gt;Which parties receive the most Community Notes?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://css-synosys.github.io/Barplots_Parties.html&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;500px&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 3&lt;/strong&gt;	Number of posts with Community Notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 3 shows the Notes of German politicians by party. Party scores are often strongly influenced by individual politicians. As shown in Figure 2, for the CSU it is mainly the official party account and that of Markus Söder. For the SPD it is mainly Ralf Stegner, member of the Bundestag, and Arno Gottschalk, financial policy spokesman for the Bremen parliamentary group. A rough analysis of the content shows that Stegner&amp;rsquo;s posts mainly relate to the Russian war in Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As before, the ranking of most Notes differs if you only look at the helpful ones. The Greens lead the ranking of Notes, closely followed by the parties of the right-wing spectrum. However, if only the helpful Notes are considered, the Greens slip to sixth place, while the SPD takes first place. Only 4% of the Notes for the Greens are rated as helpful - well below the average of around 19% for all Notes and 12% for party posts. This means that the low score for the Greens is still striking. Why is this the case?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;january-effect-coordinated-campaign-or-random-accumulation&#34;&gt;January effect: coordinated campaign or random accumulation?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://css-synosys.github.io/Party_Timeline.html&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;700px&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 4&lt;/strong&gt; Monthly distribution of (helpful) Community Notes for the parties&amp;rsquo; posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To see if the unusual pattern for the Greens can be linked to a specific event, Figure 4 shows the temporal distribution of posts with Notes. And indeed: There is a sharp increase in Notes for the Greens and the SPD in January 2025. Expressed in figures, about 29% of the 180 posts with Notes for the Greens can be attributed to this one month. The figure for the SPD is almost the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sharp increase cannot simply be explained by increased party activity. In January, the Greens published about the same number of posts as the AfD, while the SPD published only half as many. Similarly, there was no comparable increase on X following the return of Robert Habeck, the Greens&amp;rsquo; Federal Minister for Economy and Climate Protection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By comparison, since the second half of 2024 the AFD has recorded fewer Notes overall than before, with the exception of September. Although there were individual months with a high number of Notes for the AfD, in no case did a single month account for more than 14% of all Notes for the party.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unusually many Notes - coincidence or pattern?&lt;/strong&gt;
Who are the users who created and rated the Notes for the Greens and SPD in January 2025? As Notes are assigned anonymously, there is limited information available about the accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are no anomalies in the age of the accounts: The Notes for the Greens and the SPD do not come disproportionately from fresh accounts. Although there were more new accounts on X overall in January, this pattern is the same for all parties. However, the activity of the rating accounts is striking: Users sw who rated Notes for the Greens gave an average of two ratings - significantly more than the average for the Greens as a whole (around 1.3) and above the general monthly average (around 1.2). In other words: In January, not only were there an unusually high number of Notes for the Greens, but also a particularly active group of users who rated them. However, it is not possible to tell from the data whether there was any coordination between the accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of content, the Greens&amp;rsquo; posts covered a wide range of topics. These included references to political opponents, in particular CDU leader Friedrich Merz and his vote with the AfD. They also discussed the number of participants in the subsequent demonstrations, interpretations of recent poll results, criticism of Elon Musk and statements about Germany&amp;rsquo;s energy supply, some with references to Putin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Musk also played a role for the SPD, albeit to a lesser extent. Friedrich Merz was similarly prominent, as he was for the Greens. But another key issue was the statement by the SPD leadership that the party had never collaborated with Nazis - a claim that was picked up by many Notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No clear political orientation of the helpful Community Notes&lt;/strong&gt;
Community Notes are intended to highlight shortcomings in posts on X. As they can be written and rated by all registered users, the question arises as to whether party political tendencies can be inferred from them. The analysis shows that contributions from the Green Party receive a particularly high number of Notes, but only a fraction of these are rated as helpful and therefore published. It is also striking that this effect was particularly strong in January of this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does this say about registered users and their rating behaviour? For a note to be considered helpful by the bridging algorithm, the users who rate it must have previously held different viewpoints. The low rate of helpful Notes for the Greens suggests that this is not the case - the users who rate seem to be relatively politically homogeneous. Whether this is just a natural group formation or even coordinated activity - such as bots or politically motivated troll campaigns - cannot be determined with the available data. However, it should be noted that this voting behaviour is particularly directed against the Greens and also against the SPD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, the number of Notes for AfD posts has decreased in recent months. This could mean that fewer users are adding Notes to AfD posts - or that these posts are being checked less frequently. This is a development that fits with the general sentiment on X in favour of the AfD (Nenno and Lorenz-Spreen 2025).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A different picture emerges if you only look at the Notes that were actually published, i.e. rated as helpful. Here, posts from the SPD are the most common, while those from the Greens and the Left appear rather rarely. The CDU/CSU and AFD are in the middle of the field. The bridging algorithm thus ensures a certain numerical balance between parties to the left and right of the centre. However, this balance does not necessarily mean that community Notes paint an objective or neutral picture. What matters is not just how many Notes a party receives, but whether they actually correct misleading content - because ultimately the goal should be to effectively identify and label disinformation on X.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Allen, J., Martel, C., &amp;amp; Rand, D. G. (2022). Birds of a feather don’t fact-check each other: Partisanship and the evaluation of news in Twitter’s Birdwatch crowdsourced fact-checking program. Proceedings of the 2022 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, 1–19. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1145/3491102.3502040&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1145/3491102.3502040&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lasser, J., Aroyehun, S. T., Simchon, A., Carrella, F., Garcia, D., &amp;amp; Lewandowsky, S. (2022). Social media sharing of low-quality news sources by political elites. PNAS Nexus, 1(4), pgac186. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1093/pnasnexus/pgac186&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1093/pnasnexus/pgac186&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nenno, S., &amp;amp; Lorenz-Spreen, P. (2025). Do Alice Weidel and the AfD benefit from Musk’s attention on X? &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14749544&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14749544&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Renault, T., Mosleh, M., &amp;amp; Rand, D. (2025). Republicans are flagged more often than Democrats for sharing misinformation on X’s Community Notes. OSF. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.31234/osf.io/vk5yj_v2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.31234/osf.io/vk5yj_v2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Törnberg, P., &amp;amp; Chueri, J. (2025). When Do Parties Lie? Misinformation and Radical-Right Populism Across 26 Countries. The International Journal of Press/Politics, 19401612241311886. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1177/19401612241311886&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1177/19401612241311886&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wojcik, S., Hilgard, S., Judd, N., Mocanu, D., Ragain, S., Hunzaker, M. B. F., Coleman, K., &amp;amp; Baxter, J. (2022). Birdwatch: Crowd Wisdom and Bridging Algorithms can Inform Understanding and Reduce the Spread of Misinformation (No. arXiv:2210.15723). arXiv. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2210.15723&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2210.15723&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Do Alice Weidel and the AfD benefit from Musk&#39;s attention on X?</title>
      <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/post/x_election/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://css-synosys.github.io/post/x_election/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Has Elon Musk manipulated X to give the AfD more reach? He has made it clear in posts, articles and election events that he is a fan - and at the same time, Alice Weidel&amp;rsquo;s reach on X has increased significantly. Could these developments be linked? This blog post describes a data analysis in which we take a closer look at which accounts have received how much reach and whether Musk&amp;rsquo;s influence can be determined. Where does the sudden increase in Weidel&amp;rsquo;s reach on X come from?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note: This work has not yet been peer reviewed.&lt;/strong&gt; A more detailed description of the analysis, the methods, as well as the code and data can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/jcqen/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent weeks, there has been a lot of fuss about Elon Musk&amp;rsquo;s possible influence in favour of the AfD. First, on 20 December, he wrote on his platform X (formerly Twitter) that &lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/elonmusk/status/1869986946031988780&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;only the AfD can save Germany&lt;/a&gt;. On 28 December, Die Welt published a guest article by Musk in which he expressed the same position. Finally, on 9 January, he held a public conversation on X with the AfD candidate Alice Weidel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As already reported in &lt;a href=&#34;https://bsky.app/profile/jhillje.bsky.social/post/3lfckchdifs2u&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;one&lt;/a&gt; place or &lt;a href=&#34;https://bsky.app/profile/curdknupfer.bsky.social/post/3lfcp265mgs2k&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;another&lt;/a&gt;, Weidel gained a lot of reach on X. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zeit.de/politik/deutschland/2025-01/bundestag-wahlkampf-einmischung-wahlkampf-musk-elon-weidel-alice-pruefung&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The German parliamentary administration then announced&lt;/a&gt;  that it would investigate whether Musk is influencing the election campaign. At the same time, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zdf.de/nachrichten/politik/eu-kommission-elon-musk-x-algorithmus-100.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;the EU Commission&lt;/a&gt; is demanding insight into possible changes to X&amp;rsquo;s recommendation algorithms. This article analyses the possible impact of Musk&amp;rsquo;s activities on the reach of the AfD and Weidel in particular on social media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;baskerville tl f1-l f4-m f4&#34;&gt;
            &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://css-synosys.github.io/Fig_1.html&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;700px&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1&lt;/strong&gt; Number of followers of various German politicians (top) and views of Weidel&amp;rsquo;s posts with and without retweets from Elon Musk (bottom, retweets outlined in red).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Weidel&amp;rsquo;s jumps in reach often coincide with Musk&amp;rsquo;s expressions of sympathy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s start with the number of follows on X (Fig. 1, top). For the politicians Lindner, Scholz, Merz and Habeck, we see how the number usually grows: slow and steady. It is different with Weidel. We see two sharp jumps and a steady but faster increase in between. The first increase occurred around 20 December. At this time, Musk posted that only the AfD could save Germany and also mentioned the AfD in other posts. However, these were only mentions (with and without links) and not retweets. This is an important difference. In the case of a retweet, the original post also appears in Musk&amp;rsquo;s timeline and, as he is followed by over 200 million people, this automatically generates a lot of reach. With ‘mere’ mentions, those who follow Musk first have to go to the respective profile of the account mentioned and that is often a bigger hurdle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around 28 December - Musk&amp;rsquo;s contribution to Die Welt - he retweeted a post by Weidel for the first time (in which she thanked him for the guest article). This post has 15 million views (Fig. 1, below, outlined in red). However, the public conversation with Musk seems to have had a particular impact on the number of her followers. In the days leading up to 9 January, Musk mentioned and retweeted Alice Weidel several times, which earned her as many as 24 million views for one post, and on 10 January her number of followers increased by almost 150.000.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 1 shows that individual posts by Weidel that were retweeted by Musk received a large number of views. However, individual posts without retweets also have a high reach. In order to find out whether there was a specific point in time when Weidel&amp;rsquo;s views started to increase, we carried out a so-called changepoint analysis. Roughly speaking, this method is used to find out whether the data can be better described with one or two trend lines and, if there are two, where the break should be made. The analysis showed that there was already a significant break on 16 December. On that day, Olaf Scholz lost the vote of confidence in the German parliament. The two trend lines are shown in red in the lower part of Figure 1. You can see that the second line is well above the first. In the first period, Weidel&amp;rsquo;s posts received an average of almost 140.000 views, then almost 790.000.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A few retweets with a wide reach have created views for Weidel&amp;rsquo;s posts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://css-synosys.github.io/Fig_2.html&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;600px&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 2&lt;/strong&gt; Development of the views of Weidel&amp;rsquo;s posts over a period of 36 hours. Note: The post in the centre is no longer available, but it was also announced on &lt;a href=&#34;https://alice-weidel.de/aktuelles/neuer-beitrag-auf-x-com-229/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Alice Weidel&amp;rsquo;s website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s now take a closer look at Weidel&amp;rsquo;s posts. To do this, we regularly accessed X over a longer period of time so that we could not only record the absolute numbers, but also their development, i.e. how quickly they grow. Figure 2 shows the six most viewed posts by Alice Weidel and their dynamics over 36 hours. The dashed lines show the time at which Musk mentioned Weidel and the red lines show that this post was even retweeted by Musk. Two things are striking about the posts that were retweeted. Firstly, these tend to have the most views and secondly, the views only jump in these cases and this always takes place shortly after the post was retweeted by Musk. We were unable to find similar jumps for the four other politicians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://css-synosys.github.io/Fig_3.html&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;700px&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 3&lt;/strong&gt;	Engagement metrics of posts by various German politicians before and after 16 December 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 3 shows not only the views, but also retweets and likes of individual posts. The ratio of views and retweets provides an indication of the distribution of the post. If a post has many views but comparatively few retweets, then there is probably one or more accounts with a very wide reach among the retweets. In the case of Alice Weidel&amp;rsquo;s post, you can see a sharp increase in views after 16 December, but a less sharp increase in retweets. A comparison with the other four politicians also shows that it is Weidel&amp;rsquo;s views that increased after 16 December, but not her retweets. You can see the contrast when you look at Habeck in particular, whose posts receive comparatively many retweets. It seems as if he has an active base that retweets his posts, whereas with Weidel it tends to be individual accounts that use their high reach to generate views for her through retweets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The rest of the AfD has not gained as much as Weidel&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://css-synosys.github.io/Fig_4.html&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;900px&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 4&lt;/strong&gt;	Views of the posts of various AfD accounts over time. Linear y-axis in the upper diagram, logarithmic at the bottom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did only the reach of Alice Weidel&amp;rsquo;s posts experience such rapid growth or does this apply to all AfD members? Figure 4 provides information on this. It shows the views of posts by AfD members (38 in total) and Alice Weidel. At the top it is a linear measure and at the bottom a logarithmic one in which the distances gradually increase. It is clear that Weidel&amp;rsquo;s posts receive many views compared to the other AfD accounts. However, an upward trend can also be seen for the other accounts, which began at the start of December. It is difficult to spot this with the naked eye, so we have also done changepoint analyses for the posts of a few AfD accounts. However, the analysis does not show an increase comparable to that of Weidel. Even though some other AfD members and the official party accounts are experiencing an upswing on X, it is less strong and less sudden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Musk&amp;rsquo;s reposts and public statements have likely given Weidel reach
What can we conclude from this about the influence of Elon Musk on the reach of the AfD and Alice Weidel? Firstly, we need to explain the limitations of our method. As already mentioned, we collected snapshots of politicians&amp;rsquo; posts over an extended period of time. For the five discussed here, we have done this more closely since 10 January. This can be seen very clearly in Figure 1, as the points have been closer together since then. On the one hand, however, this means that there are gaps and irregularities in the snapshots and that we can say less about the dynamics before 10 January. In addition, we also have no access to the geographical origin of the users who saw Weidel&amp;rsquo;s post. This would of course be interesting, especially in the context of the upcoming federal elections. In addition to the methodological limitations, however, there is a much more fundamental problem. We have no direct access to the modes of action of X&amp;rsquo;s algorithm. As long as we do not have this, we can only collect data and deduce modes of action by means of circumstantial evidence. We also deliberately see our results only as indications that suggest an explanation, rather than evidence that clearly proves something. Against this backdrop, it is particularly important that the long-disputed obligation to provide access to research data, which is now enshrined in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.interface-eu.org/publications/researcher-access-platform-data-under-dsa-questions-and-answers&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Art. 40 of the Digital Service Act&lt;/a&gt;, is brought to life. It is a shame that researchers had to wait so long for the Commission&amp;rsquo;s delegated act. &lt;a href=&#34;https://ec.europa.eu/info/law/better-regulation/have-your-say/initiatives/13817-Delegated-Regulation-on-data-access-provided-for-in-the-Digital-Services-Act_enBut&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;But now it is here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alice Weidel has rapidly increased both the views of her posts and the number of her followers in the weeks since 16 and 20 December. She has gained almost 400.000 followers in this period - that is more than Friedrich Merz has in total. Her posts also have a greater reach than those of any other German politician. It seems very obvious that this has to do with Musk&amp;rsquo;s activities. The pattern of posts he has retweeted from Weidel in particular suggests this. Her views, on the other hand, were more likely to have been influenced by the frequent mentions by Musk and ultimately the public talk between the two. The most obvious conclusion is that Musk&amp;rsquo;s mentions, retweets and the conversation have given Weidel an increased reach, from which her subsequent posts that are not retweeted by Musk now also benefit. We found no evidence of an adjustment of the algorithm in Weidel&amp;rsquo;s favour, even though it is known that Musk&amp;rsquo;s statements on X are particularly visible and a retweet from him can lead to a shift in discourse. The same applies to other AfD accounts. An increase can be measured for a few of them, but it is less noticeable than for Weidel. Overall, however, it should be noted that the explanations are not mutually exclusive. Just because Weidel&amp;rsquo;s upswing can also be explained by Musk&amp;rsquo;s AfD-friendly posts does not mean that potential changes to the algorithm could not have led to even more, but perhaps more subtle, changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So far, the effect seems to be limited to X&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://css-synosys.github.io/Fig_5.html&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;900px&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 5&lt;/strong&gt;	Views of posts by various German politicians on Facebook, Instagram, TikTok and X.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, an integration of the results in the larger field of social media platforms. Figure 5 shows the views of Weidel&amp;rsquo;s posts and those of the other four politicians on Facebook, Instagram, TikTok and X. Firstly, it can be seen that the views for Facebook are the lowest and those on the other platforms are still more comparable. You can also see that the views of individual politicians&amp;rsquo; posts can vary greatly depending on the platform. For example, Scholz is more popular on TikTok than Habeck, but the opposite is true on Instagram and X.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alice Weidel expressed her thanks to Musk for his article in Die Welt not only on X, but also on the other platforms. These posts often received an exceptionally high number of views. However, it is not unusual for individual posts to receive a lot of coverage. Lindner&amp;rsquo;s TikTok post showing him being attacked with shaving foam also received over 25 million views and individual posts by Habeck or Lindner achieved even more reach on Facebook or Instagram than those by Weidel. Nevertheless, we carried out a changepoint analysis to find out whether Weidel&amp;rsquo;s posts also received more views on other platforms after 20 December. Again, the analysis did not reveal any conspicuous results. So far, we cannot find any strong evidence that Weidel&amp;rsquo;s popularity on X is also spreading to other platforms. As things stand, the Musk effect is therefore limited to X.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We would like to thank Matthias Kettemann for his helpful feedback. The data was last updated on 27/01/2025 and data collection is ongoing. A version of this report was published in German at the Digital Society Blog of the Alexander von Humboldt Institut für Internet und Gesellschaft &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hiig.de/musk-x-und-afd/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. A more detailed description of the analysis, the methods, as well as the code and data can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/jcqen/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New multi-author preprint about who should govern online environments</title>
      <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/post/choice_architects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://css-synosys.github.io/post/choice_architects/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this multi-author paper, spearheaded by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mpib-berlin.mpg.de/person/friederike-stock/419405&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Friederike Stock&lt;/a&gt;, and as part of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://jrp.pscholars.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Junior Researcher Program&lt;/a&gt; with young researchers from 26 different countries and the project was supervised by Philipp Lorenz-Spreen. Little is known about who users themselves think should control their online environments, and under what circumstances. In our preregistered study, participants across 26 countries (N = 11,686) decided between combinations of three possible choice architects—governments, platforms, and individuals—and three objectives—societal, commercial, and personal—in seven real-world contexts. Across all countries, people strongly prefer to set their own rules for their online choice architectures. Find the full preprint &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/preprints/osf/haqu9&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Research Explores News Values in Perceived Misinformation Across 24 Countries</title>
      <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/post/fake_news_24/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://css-synosys.github.io/post/fake_news_24/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sami Nenno, Postdoc in the Junior Research Group Computational Social Science at SynoSys, Center Synergy of Systems, has co-authored an insightful new paper, All the (Fake) News That’s Fit to Share? News Values in Perceived Misinformation Across Twenty-Four Countries. Co-written with Cornelius Puschmann, the study has been published in The International Journal of Press/Politics and investigates the relationship between journalistic news values and perceived misinformation in diverse national contexts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The research addresses a notable gap in the understanding of how misinformation is shaped and perceived globally. While much of the previous scholarship has focused on misinformation within WEIRD (Western, Educated, Industrialized, Rich, and Democratic) countries, this study expands the scope by including both WEIRD and non-WEIRD regions. Using a dataset of over 770,000 Facebook-shared URLs flagged as misinformation by users, the study analyzes the prevalence of five key news values: conflict, negativity, proximity, individualization, and informativeness. Through computational analysis, the authors explore how these news values appear in flagged and unflagged content and assess their variation across 24 countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The research reveals that flagged content, often perceived as misinformation, tends to emphasize conflict and negativity more strongly than unflagged content. Other news values, such as proximity and individualization, also appear more prominently in flagged items, though with varying intensity. Significant differences in the prevalence of news values were observed between WEIRD and non-WEIRD countries. For instance, proximity and negativity were found to be more pronounced in WEIRD countries, whereas individualization was more prevalent in non-WEIRD contexts. The study also highlights unique patterns in countries such as the United States and Brazil, where conflict and negativity were particularly dominant in flagged content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The findings challenge existing frameworks of news values, which were primarily developed within Western contexts, by showing that these models may not fully account for the diversity of global media landscapes. This emphasizes the need for more inclusive theoretical models that better reflect regional and cultural differences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study contributes to the growing field of misinformation research by providing a global perspective on how news values intersect with perceived misinformation. It highlights the influence of journalistic styles and national media systems on the characteristics of flagged content, offering valuable insights for academics, journalists, and policymakers seeking to address the challenges posed by misinformation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This publication was part of Sami Nenno&amp;rsquo;s PhD project and was written during his time at the University of Bremen and at the Alexander von Humboldt Institute for Internet and Society. He recently joined Synosys to continue his work. The paper is accessible online at &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/19401612241311893&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this link&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Study Reveals Who’s Most Vulnerable to Misinformation—and why</title>
      <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/post/misinformation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://css-synosys.github.io/post/misinformation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our junior research group leader Philipp Lorenz-Spreen, whose work focuses on the digital information environment and among other things on misinformation, has co-authored a comprehensive meta-analysis of over 256,000 decisions from thousands of participants that sheds light on who is most susceptible to misinformation and the factors behind it. Their research reveals that susceptibility depends less on formal education and more on individual and contextual factors, such as age, analytical thinking, and political alignment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Older adults and those with strong analytical skills tend to discern truth from falsehood better, though they are also more skeptical, which means they classify more news as false overall. A tendency called “true news bias” emerges when people encounter news aligning with their political beliefs or previously seen content, making them more prone to believe information without scrutiny. These findings offer valuable insights for his further studies of the spreading dynamics of misinformation and the development of interventions that help people to navigate the information environment of the internet. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2409329121&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
