<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | CSS-Synosys</title>
    <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://css-synosys.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://css-synosys.github.io/media/logo_huadcf591365e3e14dbad9136ac9a06bd6_438486_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Democracy and Digital Media</title>
      <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/project/digitalmedia/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://css-synosys.github.io/project/digitalmedia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Digital media has changed the way public spheres function around the world, specifically in the information environment of the internet. Moving from mostly one-to-many communication to a many-to-many system has increased its complexity. In addition, big platforms are curating information flows algorithmically and optimize them for engagement. Our goal is to better understand how those transitions are affecting democracies globally and political behaviour in particular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Phenomena such as affective polarization, the rise of populism, the spread of misinformation and diminishing trust in institutions are potential developments of concern. For us, tools from data science, but also causal inference and experimentation, are essential to achieve this goal of empirically describing the complex mechanisms at play between human behavior, technology and politics.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FEDORA Project Secures Funding to Explore Post-COVID Ecological Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/project/fedora/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://css-synosys.github.io/project/fedora/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are thrilled to announce that our project, “FEDORA - Federated Network Modeling of Ecological Complex Dynamical Patterns in Post-COVID,” has successfully secured funding. just for testing purpuse i wrote this line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This pioneering initiative aims to advance the understanding of how ecological systems are affected by complex dynamical patterns emerging in the aftermath of the COVID-19 pandemic.
The FEDORA project will focus on federated network modeling to examine these complex patterns, particularly those related to wearable technology, sleep, and persistent symptoms observed post-COVID. Through a collaborative approach, the project will harness cutting-edge data and modeling techniques to reveal new insights into the long-term impacts of COVID-19 on ecological and human health. dfgdfgdfg&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The FEDORA project will focus on federated network modeling to examine these complex patterns, particularly those related to wearable technology, sleep, and persistent symptoms observed post-COVID. Through a collaborative approach, the project will harness cutting-edge data and modeling techniques to reveal new insights into the long-term impacts of COVID-19 on ecological and human health. dfgdfgdfg dfgdfgdfg dfgdfgdfg&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our interdisciplinary team will work together to develop innovative models that integrate data from various sources, creating a comprehensive understanding of the interplay between ecological and health dynamics in the post-COVID world. The insights gained from this project will not only contribute to scientific knowledge but also guide future public health strategies and ecological conservation efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We look forward to sharing more updates as the project progresses and invite the community to stay tuned for further developments.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
