<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | CSS-Synosys</title>
    <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://css-synosys.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://css-synosys.github.io/media/logo_hu_8314fbf1d9759f2e.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Democracy and Digital Media</title>
      <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/project/digitalmedia/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://css-synosys.github.io/project/digitalmedia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Digital media has changed the way public spheres function around the world, specifically in the information environment of the internet. Moving from mostly one-to-many communication to a many-to-many system has increased its complexity. In addition, big platforms are curating information flows algorithmically and optimize them for engagement. Our goal is to better understand how those transitions are affecting democracies globally and political behaviour in particular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Phenomena such as affective polarization, the rise of populism, the spread of misinformation and diminishing trust in institutions are potential developments of concern. For us, tools from data science, but also causal inference and experimentation, are essential to achieve this goal of empirically describing the complex mechanisms at play between human behavior, technology and politics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The central research questions are: How is public discourse shaped by social networks and sorting algorithms, and how does it benefit certain rhetoric? How do generated images affect attention and emotions and how do they reinforce certain narratives more than others? Establishing causality between these factors in such complex socio-technical systems is an overarching challenge that we aim to address.
To achieve this, we are convinced that looking at those systems from various angles is crucial. While the overarching questions span the whole research groups, we are composed of a variety of disciplinary backgrounds and methods. Digitalization is not only impacting social systems, but also expanding the methods for studying them and enabling us to cover a spectrum of measurements of human behavior between micro and macro levels, ranging from online experiments to field studies in social media and large-scale platform data analysis, while computer simulations may help connect the scales.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Psychology of Digital Propaganda</title>
      <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/project/propaganda/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://css-synosys.github.io/project/propaganda/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Across the globe, worries are growing about the unchecked power of social media and manipulative content, further enhanced by generative AI. As viral content is believed to shape public opinions, the question of how exactly these forces influence individual and collective beliefs, attitudes, and behavior has never been more urgent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our research focuses on Digital Propaganda, which we understand as orchestrated efforts by various actors—be they political, corporate, or ideological—to influence the public for their own benefit. Leveraging user data and the attention-maximization of feed algorithms, today’s social media and digital platforms enable these campaigns to operate with greater precision and scale than ever before, far surpassing what was possible with television or radio alone. By personalizing messages, repeating them relentlessly, simplifying complex issues into stark narratives, and amplifying emotionally charged content, this new digital environment intensifies the potential to shock, polarize, and manipulate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although these tactics clearly exploit known cognitive biases and emotional reactivity, we still lack precise causal evidence of how exactly they shape people’s feelings, beliefs, and behaviors. Many assume digital propaganda wields manipulative power, yet a deeper understanding of which elements of human cognition and behavior are truly affected—and in what ways—remains elusive. Through large-scale experimentation, computational modeling, and psychologically driven and AI-supported analysis of social media content, we aim to bring robust empirical evidence to the table to uncover these mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, by bridging these knowledge gaps, we seek to lay the groundwork for evidence-based psychological interventions that empower individuals to recognize and resist manipulative strategies. At the same time, our findings will offer crucial insights for policymakers and platform regulators, helping them craft balanced measures that safeguard users from harmful content while upholding the essential values of open dialogue and informed participation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Text as Data</title>
      <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/project/nlp/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://css-synosys.github.io/project/nlp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Big data and computational power are growing fast, and it&amp;rsquo;s not just the big tech companies making use of it. Social sciences are also benefiting from these advances. Natural Language Processing (NLP) has come a long way, and now researchers can analyze text data in ways that were impossible just a few decades ago. Social media posts, transcripts of political debates, and parliamentary speeches are now valuable data sources for studying human behavior, political discourse, and societal trends. This opens up a bunch of new questions and gives us new ways to study them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our “Text-as-Data” project uses NLP methods to analyze how politicians communicate across social media and other channels. We investigate the dynamics of disinformation, examining how false or misleading information spreads and evolves within political communication. Understanding these patterns is crucial in an age of eroding trust in democratic institutions and polarized societies. We also study how different groups of citizens are addressed, shedding light on patterns of political inequality in messaging. This is important for assessing whether political communication reflects or exacerbates existing social divides, and for ensuring that all voices are equally valued in public discourse. Additionally, we analyze whether there has been an ideological shift in political discourse in recent years, helping us understand how political narratives adapt to societal changes and shape public opinion. By addressing these challenges, our research aims to contribute to a deeper understanding of contemporary political dynamics and the role of communication in shaping democracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To answer these questions, we are creating new methods to combine data from different sources. This lets us find connections and trends across different types of communication. This approach helps us understand political communication better. It also gives us new tools and frameworks for analyzing complex social phenomena.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
