<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Democracy | CSS-Synosys</title>
    <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/tag/democracy/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://css-synosys.github.io/tag/democracy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Democracy</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://css-synosys.github.io/media/logo_hu_8314fbf1d9759f2e.png</url>
      <title>Democracy</title>
      <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/tag/democracy/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>New replication study examines the influence of digital media on democracy</title>
      <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/post/replication/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://css-synosys.github.io/post/replication/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;© [AI] ChatGPT / MPG adapted from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mpg.de/24519906/digital-media-a-threat-to-democracy&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;press release&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The research team systematically replicated the methodology of the original study and used an updated dataset with studies up to March 2024. The results confirm the findings of the original study: Digital media have many problematic effects on democratic processes, in addition to positive ones. On the one hand, they promote political participation and facilitate access to information. On the other hand, they increase polarization, mistrust in institutions, and populist movements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A recent research paper by the Institute for Replication (I4R) analyzes and reviews the results of the 2023 study, ‘A Systematic Review of Worldwide Causal and Correlational Evidence on Digital Media and Democracy,’ by Lorenz-Spreen et al. The replication study, conducted by researchers from Tongji University, the University of Cambridge, and Duke University, confirms the original findings on the relationships between digital media and democracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The replication study supports our findings, and the worrying trends continue,” explains Philipp Lorenz-Spreen, research group leader for Computational Social Science at TU Dresden and research scientist at the Max Planck Institute for Human Development (MPIB) in Berlin. He and Lisa Oswald – both working at the Center for Adaptive Rationality – led the 2023 study. Postdoctoral researcher Lisa Oswald underscores the significance of these findings. “The correlative evidence is mounting that digital media can negatively influence political processes – we see increased polarization, rising mistrust in democratic institutions and media, and a proliferation of misinformation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Replication study: &lt;a href=&#34;https://ideas.repec.org/p/zbw/i4rdps/206.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://ideas.repec.org/p/zbw/i4rdps/206.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Original study: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41562-022-01460-1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41562-022-01460-1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Democracy and Digital Media</title>
      <link>https://css-synosys.github.io/project/digitalmedia/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://css-synosys.github.io/project/digitalmedia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Digital media has changed the way public spheres function around the world, specifically in the information environment of the internet. Moving from mostly one-to-many communication to a many-to-many system has increased its complexity. In addition, big platforms are curating information flows algorithmically and optimize them for engagement. Our goal is to better understand how those transitions are affecting democracies globally and political behaviour in particular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Phenomena such as affective polarization, the rise of populism, the spread of misinformation and diminishing trust in institutions are potential developments of concern. For us, tools from data science, but also causal inference and experimentation, are essential to achieve this goal of empirically describing the complex mechanisms at play between human behavior, technology and politics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The central research questions are: How is public discourse shaped by social networks and sorting algorithms, and how does it benefit certain rhetoric? How do generated images affect attention and emotions and how do they reinforce certain narratives more than others? Establishing causality between these factors in such complex socio-technical systems is an overarching challenge that we aim to address.
To achieve this, we are convinced that looking at those systems from various angles is crucial. While the overarching questions span the whole research groups, we are composed of a variety of disciplinary backgrounds and methods. Digitalization is not only impacting social systems, but also expanding the methods for studying them and enabling us to cover a spectrum of measurements of human behavior between micro and macro levels, ranging from online experiments to field studies in social media and large-scale platform data analysis, while computer simulations may help connect the scales.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
